Here in just a moment, I'm sorry, I have,
I have a here we go and recording has
started and we're letting people in from
the, the, the waiting room.
So people will be able to join here in
just a few moments.
Just as a reminder to everyone is this is
the meeting for the Equity Access and
Cultural Considerations Committee.
The meeting is being recorded.
My name is Dominic Zurlo with the
Department of Health and we are here with
the Chair Desbah.
And with that,
since we are on time and moving forward,
I'll go ahead turn it on over to you,
Desbah.
So thank you.
Hello.
Thank you, Dominic and DoH admins,
really appreciate your time.
So for today,
we just kind of wanted to go over a
couple of things from the last meeting.
We did have it announced that we did get
the $630,
000 appropriated money signed in from
Governor Michelle Lujan Grisham.
And that is, yeah, that's been signed in.
It is going to go into effect this July
for the fiscal year, I believe.
And it does.
I wrote the notes on this.
There's a specific term that I now have
forgotten what it is, but it just,
it's the money won't go away.
The money will just stay there until it
is, until it runs out.
And not only that,
but it also cannot be like recharged so
that it's not gonna come back.
So any other money that we are gonna be
looking towards anything has to be
earmarked again.
But those are good.
Those are good things in the sense that
even though it's gonna be going into
effect in July for the fiscal year for
2027,
it will the the funds will be there and
it's not going to,
it's not going to revert back into,
it's not going to get reabsorbed back
into any other.
It's not going to get reabsorbed.
So does does Bob, sorry to interrupt.
It's non reverting is the term you wrote
non reverting.
Yes, Yeah.
But it's hard to remember.
I always have to look it up too.
So yeah, I had it in my notes.
And then I realized that these are not
notes that I wrote down,
the ones that I picked up.
So in any case, that's all good.
But with that,
that means that we have to figure out now
how that money is going to be distributed
to the various patients that will be
seeking medical psilocybin for treatment
in the coming year.
So with that,
we're looking into potentially is that
going to go like how is it's gonna,
how is it gonna be allocated?
How is it going to be distributed?
Is it going to be based completely on
income only where the national poverty
rate threshold is currently at night 15
thousand 15,960.
I believe I had it up here again too.
And then I I lost it.
Yes, $15,960 for one individual,
two people 21,643 people 27,320.
And even though those are the federal
poverty guidelines, we all know that $15,
000 isn't anything, not not even a,
not even someone who needs the money can
subsist on $15,000 anymore.
That's just absurd.
But what what we're trying to look at
though,
is what kind of coverage a person would
need based on those metrics.
And if we're actually looking at that,
are we looking at rural areas?
Is it gonna be based on a demographic
like geography and how that's gonna look?
So, you know,
this is where we definitely need outside
input from everybody to kind of just say
how we're going to to allocate this money.
And that's specifically with the equity
fund.
We're currently now trying to figure out
just to kind of touch base a little bit
with what happened in the last board
meeting.
So this is a committee meeting.
So the board meeting is that we're gonna
start looking at the training,
what are the requirements for licensure
and facilitators,
what that looks like grandfathering in
out of state certifications,
what kind of practicums, etcetera.
So definitely look for the training
committee meeting that is going to be
happening, I believe in April.
But that's the next thing that we're
gonna be trying to item on the agenda for
the board is what that's gonna look like.
In the meantime,
trying to make sure that we have
something to recommend to the board,
to the Department of Health.
It's gonna go through 2, two things.
Committee recommends to the board.
Board then recommends to the DoH how it's
what it's gonna look like for the year
2027.
So we definitely need a lot of input in
that.
And then for those who are concerned
about Native federally recognized tribes
input,
we are trying to get in the process of
getting meetings with tribal liaisons
from the Department of Health,
getting that set up,
getting some invites with the governors
from the different pueblos.
We're also looking into having an in
person committee meeting in the future.
It's Santa Fe,
so we need to set that up as well.
So if there's anybody of the participants
who have kind of an idea of what
necessarily we should look at so that we
can recommend it to the board,
how we're gonna look at allocating the
money, What does that look like?
Are we covering like 100% of a treatment?
Are we covering 50%?
What is the breakdown and the threshold?
So we can go ahead and try Hannah Rose.
Awesome.
Let's see.
Hannah, I have enabled your mic.
You can speak when ready.
And just as a reminder,
the mic icon is should be up at the top
right part of the banner on teams.
Thank you.
I've done this so many times and then you
know the mic just thanks and where it's
it's elusive.
I know I was really I was like where I've
already done this.
OK Hi, my name is Hanna Rose, BSW student,
first generation quid and data.
I'm really glad to be having this
discussion supporting you all in this
from a social work and like,
you know perspective who's not from
tribal land but cares about Yeah,
how are we going to use these resources?
One thing that came to mind, Desbe,
is that how I say your name,
Desbe Desba Desba.
Sorry,
I couldn't I didn't have the the word
written out your name written out that's
BA.
When you were speaking and wondering
about paying 100% or not,
what came to mind in is the importance of
investing in our health and even if it's
just a small monetary amount,
the fact that low income populations will
value their money more preciously and
maybe be in a lack mentality.
I've witnessed some magic happen around
people that then invest in their health
through whatever budget they can.
So I guess I just want to name that and
take that into consideration because it
trains our culture to budget, right?
It trains our culture to consider that
this investment is is no,
I don't want to say no different,
but it can normalize that like, oh,
you're willing to if the if the person's
willing to go to a pharmacy and pay the
co-pay for, you know, the antidepressant,
then let's normalize being willing to
come into this program and pay a co-pay
to normalize that investment of health.
And I feel complete in that share for now.
Thank you.
All right, thanks, Hannah.
And next we've got Denali Wilson.
Denali, I've enabled your mic.
You can speak when ready.
Hi, everyone.
I have a couple of thoughts.
My name is Denali Wilson.
I'm the Director of Strategic Support for
Healing Advocacy funds in New Mexico,
based in Las Cruces.
And so I think we have to think about the
equity fund in conversation with the work
that's being done to make sure that
treatment is covered by Medicaid and by
private insurance like that.
That is that has to be a part of our
vision for equity and access.
And I and I think the two work hand in
hand.
So there's a couple of possibilities.
You know,
one possibility is that when the program
is up and running on the December
timeline,
maybe we are not in a place with the
state Medicaid office,
the health care authority that there is
coverage are my hope is that we are if
we're not then I think we have a
conversation about covering 100% of
treatment.
But, but I think, you know, $630,000 for,
you know,
a whole treatment for someone which can
range, you know,
upwards of $3000 for all the cost rate
that that's not nothing.
But, you know,
it certainly doesn't go as far as as us
paying for the,
what I what I would recommend is thinking
about paying for the 1.
You know, until there's FDA approval,
you know,
they're not ever going to be covered part
of the care,
which is the administration and the
medicine itself.
You know,
that's a lot of time for providers that
they're not going to be able to bill to
Medicaid or other private insurance.
And so if we think about the equity fund
as a gap cover for that part of the care
model that can't be insured,
can't be covered by insurance at the
moment,
like in the current state of the law and
the FDAI think that that, you know,
provides us with the ability to provide
care to to so many more people.
I think too, you know, there,
there are some in other subcommittees,
you know,
the end of life care subcommittee,
there is consideration of including and
I'm really excited about the conversation
to include in care and in eligibility for
care family members who are caretakers
for for those directly receiving
palliative care.
And, and I think that that, you know,
is a real opportunity for some
transformational healing at end of life.
And I'm really excited about that and
have the question of how that fits within
equity and access.
You know,
I think there's a lot there's going to
within a medically integrated model.
There's going to be more question as to
eligibility, you know,
if you aren't receiving palliative care,
but you are a caretaker, you know,
I'm using that as an example of potential
populations where the equity funds maybe
is needed to cover,
cover individuals who are eligible to
participate within the program that we've
designed.
But can't that that,
that their care won't be able to be
covered by by Medicaid or or private
insurance.
And then I just wanted to mention as a,
another thought,
the way that the statute is written is
that the,
is that the eligibility like the only
criteria is around income.
And I'm,
I'm really excited that we're thinking
about other considerations.
I just want to flag that, you know,
it might be helpful to get the
department's legal team's perspective on
whether like what are the boundaries of
what can be,
what can be the rules for eligibility if
the statute only says based on income.
And you know,
I'd love to have a conversation, you know,
if if those are were limited to those
eligibility criteria, you know,
is this something that we we talk about
expanding in a clean up version of the
bill next year or or in a future
legislative session?
Awesome, Thank you.
And then I think Dominic,
you had some corrections or information
to add.
Yeah, thank you.
Despa not not corrections,
it's just really to kind of go with that
is Denali,
you're right on track is we really are
looking at this when you know as far As
for the equity fund is really something
that falls outside of when we can get
insurers to pay and Medicaid to pay.
And so it really is looking outside of
that aspect.
So it would first be trying,
it's like what happens when people go in
for other medical appointments,
it would be trying to get reimbursement
through there.
And then if that is not possible,
then the equity fund would help fill that
gap on it.
And, and part of it is yes,
even though the,
the language does just talk about the
income requirements,
it doesn't mean that that's the only
potential requirement because the these
other aspects such as transportation,
care for other family members,
we can still do it based upon that income
aspect.
It's just another portion of it because
it doesn't restrict how it shall be used.
It's it really just says fund treatments
of qualified patients who meet the income
requirements.
So it's just going to be a question of
how we were that to ensure that these
other aspects fit in within it,
including that,
you know that that question of, you know,
when we have somebody who's in a rural or
frontier area,
how do we ensure that they're able to do
that?
Because again,
if we're looking at a difference in
income, for example, even from like,
we have to figure out how to put it in
there so that somebody who is closer into
a potential provider, you know,
they may not actually qualify where
somebody who's 100 miles out in a rural
community may,
because there's no provider within that
area.
And so that's where we have to kind of
figure some of those aspects out of how
do we actually, you know,
word that language correctly to make sure
that we include that income portion while
still meeting the needs within the other
areas.
So I'm glad you're already thinking about
that because that's some of what I,
I have been struggling a little bit with,
of how do we ensure that we can do this
in these other ways.
But we want to try to include as much as
we can so that we can be treating not
just the person, but really, you know,
that that community, so to speak,
the family and the community,
not just the individual,
because we know healing does not take
place in a vacuum and other people in
supportive folks are need to be included
in this.
Anyway, I hope that helps.
Thank you, Dominic.
So based on like what has been discussed
so far and for those who are just kind of
joined in,
we're just trying to figure out what it
looks like to use or just someone else
want to talk.
Who is it based on just like the criteria,
like what is the criteria that's involved
in someone using and utilizing the equity
fund?
And what it sounds like from what it
sounds like from Dominic is that and I
and I think I want to put in kind of a
little bit of an example where this might
be the case to include both what Denali
was saying and Hana in,
in this kind of perspective.
Is there someone else that wanted to or
is or did we just forget to lower our
hands?
Hannah has No,
I think they've just raised their hands
again.
So OK, yeah,
we can circle back to them whenever.
Well,
So what I was thinking of possibly like
just to kind of illustrate Dominic's
point is and to ever to kind of wrap
everything together as a scenario is,
you know,
we have the the poverty threshold at 15,
960.
So we had someone at 15,900 for instance,
right.
Then they let's just say for all that,
But I think it to me,
it sounds like it's a series of flow
chart scenarios where you know,
especially if the person you know, one,
one has to happen with the other, right.
So generally speaking, someone at that,
at that, at that level,
whatever the threshold is for Medicaid,
Medicare, that kicks in.
So if someone is on Medicaid Medicare,
then they definitely are eligible for X
amount of treatment.
And I think that that would then also
kind of kick in the copay.
So that I think is just more an
understanding of what happens when
someone doesn't meet any of the criteria
and maybe someone can kind of clarify the
little more.
So I guess the fund may or may not kick
in for the gap.
If it's someone who already is at the
poverty line,
maybe they have no insurance would
probably be one of the one of the issues.
But if they do have Medicaid,
then they definitely would be covered.
But what is maybe that copay look like if
that's already established,
then that kind of sort of covers Hana's
point of investment,
which I think is really important.
And I did kind of raise that question for
her because I do think that that really
is a thing.
You know,
we do value something that we put in.
We put our own sweat and equity,
et cetera into something, right?
So I think that that's a valid point.
However,
I only thing that I would say that may or
may not happen is if for instance the
medicator ready dictates that this
treatment is covered.
And then of course,
that goes into the cost of the treatment
itself.
And at this point,
I think we don't know what that looks
like.
I know Denali put out the number of like
$3000.
I actually don't know if someone has like
a,
a figure from either Oregon or Colorado
or just kind of a ballpark figure what
that looks like.
You know,
maybe the cost of a treatment is actually
$500.
Maybe it actually really is $3000 and
that would depend, you know, per dose.
So what is that?
I guess market value,
all these all this terminology that I
myself am not really entirely familiar
with.
But I think all of that in consideration
is what then would dictate, say,
what Medicaid covers and how much of it,
how much a copay would be for someone who
is is eligible for this treatment.
But to the point of the family that's
involved, yes,
that is definitely an issue where,
you know,
the household member is like two or three,
right?
So I'm,
I'm a household member of two and I would
need someone to take care of my child if
I didn't have that affordable available
to me, right?
So what would that look like and how much
is that based on like market value for
someone to take care of that person?
Is it gonna be someone that is available
in house or you know, we give that person,
let's say a treatment is anywhere from
4:00 to 6:00 hours, you know, at a time.
So then that's, that's $15.
00 an hour 4 * 6.
You know,
I'm so I'm not sure that this is I think
are the things that we kind of have to
look like.
Are we going to,
if the treatment itself is, say $5 copay,
but I need someone to take care of my kid
while I'm going into this,
this treatment and, and sitting in,
then I'm adding an additional 4 to 6
hours, possibly 6.
And is it even more?
Depending on, you know,
how long it takes for the patient to
actually go through the process,
it might take 6 to 10 hours.
So is there like a cut off.
And, and I don't know, I mean,
are these the kinds of things that we're
having to look at Dominic?
And if so,
like that's where my brain is going,
that's where it's wandering to when it
comes to what's the cost of something?
Is it fair market value?
Is there like a cut off?
Is there, you know, travel, for instance,
if you know,
if I was out in in Abiquiu and the
closest facilitator was in Santa Fe,
that's like an hour and a half.
And So what does that look like for
transportation?
Hopefully there would be someone in
Espanola that I could potentially go to,
which would be closer.
But as we all know,
if you're in Rio Arriba County and you
get called into to to jury duty,
it's always in Tierra Maria.
And so it's like 2 hours, right?
So what is that?
Those kinds of things are interesting to
look at when it comes to what's ruled
travel,
transportation and taking care of someone
else.
So I think from what it sounds like that
maybe the equity fund would be the best
use might be for those situations where
you have a person who has a child or is
taking care of someone else and they
really need to have that support
surrounding them because the cost of the
treatment might already be taken care of
with the Medicaid.
Now that might change when it's someone
who is not insured.
And that's the part that I'm not sure of.
And I think those are the things maybe
that Dominic that the I'm saying,
Dominic at all the board are looking for
recommendations in how we use the equity
fund.
So if anybody else wanted to chime in.
All right, let's see.
I see Hannah's.
Hannah's got her hand up again.
So Hannah, let's see your mic is enabled.
You can unmute one.
Ready.
Thank you,
Desbaugh and thank you Dominic for
clarifying these equity fund details.
As you both were speaking,
some more ideas came through from a
social work perspective.
So in social work we when we begin to
work with the client,
we perform a bio psychosocial spiritual
assessment.
And what I'm wondering is maybe there
could be an assessment process that's
created specifically for this context and
maybe that looks similar to your idea,
Desba,
around making this equity fund for the
rural marginalized population,
since it's limited,
since this is out of pocket to me that
that really distributes,
distributes power to our rural
communities, our native land communities,
these marginalized populations,
low income communities in a way that
shows how much we care and value
diversity, equity and inclusion.
So I really like that idea, Desva.
And I did some prompting about creating a,
an assessment plan just for this with
Gemini AI,
as social workers were encouraged to work
with AI in, in this kind of context.
And what I can do,
because it's a lot to read right now,
is just maybe share that somewhere in the
text, what, or in the chat,
just so there could be a written example
of, of what AI responded to.
And I gave a very specific prompt for
this exact situation.
No, I, I would suggest, yeah, sorry,
go ahead.
Yeah, Hannah, Hi, this is Hari at DoH.
What you could do is we do as we always
do,
put the medical psilocybin e-mail address
in there for public comments.
And,
and we'll share that again at the end and
we'll put in the chat in just a bit.
But what you can do is send that document
up to up to 3 pages and you can e-mail
that to us and that will go into the
minutes as part of public comment as well.
And so that Desbaugh has access to it as
well.
Great.
I will do that.
OK, thank you.
We had some other.
Was it Hannah Denali?
Hi.
Yeah, Denali, you can go ahead.
Yeah, just want to echo, I,
I neglected to mention folks who are
uninsured as in the overview of, you know,
where the equity fund triggers and that's,
that's a tremendous need in population.
So thank you to the department and others
who,
who reminded everyone of of that piece.
I wanted to explore.
You know, I,
one of the things that I've been trying
to imagine is like how,
how do we make sure that we're,
we are reducing as much as possible the
burden on patients and navigating the
bureaucracy of this program, right?
And so I,
I'd love to see a US create a system
where we don't have an additional step
that we're requesting of,
of patients to apply to the treatment
equity fund.
I think some of the barriers and
conversations that we've had are,
you know, that this,
the money has to stay really separate
from the healthcare authority and
Medicaid for federal legal reasons.
So one model that I proposed that I don't
think is workable is, you know,
that if somebody is eligible for Medicaid,
then then they are, you know,
deemed eligible without a separate
application requirement for the equity
funds.
And I think that the trouble is that
there can't be,
we can't really involve healthcare
authority.
Maybe someone from the department can
jump in and and clarify that.
But,
but I think 1 potentially workable
solution is that, and,
and I think this exists already within
some of our care models,
especially in substance use and substance
use treatment,
is that the funding could go directly to
the provider who is then committed based
on the funding to providing treatment at
no cost.
You know, and,
and it's up to their billing team, right?
That like they bill Medicaid and then
whatever the balance would come from,
would come from the equity fund.
Again, just thinking about the, the,
the well, I, I guess this would work too,
right?
Like if somebody came in and was
uninsured, right,
then their billing team would cover the
whole cost.
But that maybe if the funding goes
directly to providers who rate this,
this the system,
DoH could set up a system for RFPs for,
you know, and,
and that's a way to to prioritize rural
areas.
And then, you know,
the requirement is that they commit to
providing treatment at no cost.
OK, all right.
Oh, sorry, does.
But did you want to respond to that
before we go to Kate?
We'll go to Kate first.
OK, cool.
All right, Kate Hawk,
I've enabled your mic.
You can talk when ready.
Yeah.
Hi everybody.
So just seems like now we're sketching
out the factors.
There's a lot of what ifs and unknowns,
but you know,
we at least want to identify all these
things that are are needed and in some
situations and then we'll find out well,
what's what can be covered from this pot
of money or this system and what isn't.
And as,
as I'm glad that everybody keeps
mentioning all through this process,
rural communities is,
I know they're often left out.
I think they're one of the unknowns is,
are people in the tribes really going to
want this?
And I know they just got a couple of
members of the Pahuaki tribe to
participate in the research,
Larry Lehman's, you know, research there.
But you know, as of now,
it's not something people are clamoring
for.
But if people start finding it's
available and getting results,
then there could be a lot more interest.
But right now we just don't know.
So I know we're,
we're just taking the steps that we can
take being right in the middle of doing
taxes right now.
I will say like if there's plenty of
money and we can cover babysitters and
you know, mileage and all that, great.
Otherwise, you know,
if we can cover some of the big pieces
like, you know,
facilitators or some of the major pieces,
you know,
without having to do quite so much
paperwork,
maybe that's the mood I'm in today just
but you know, we'll see where,
where it's going.
And I think the other thing about making
it accessible is models,
like can there be models that really
include a lot of effective group work,
group work that's not just more
economical,
but there's actually more effective and
then including more peer, you know,
community people who have the skills that
are needed.
Not necessarily, you know,
a bunch of college and licensing that's
not particularly relevant.
So all of those things are going to go
into, you know,
what makes this accessible.
And thank you.
Love being part of this process.
Yeah.
I'm gonna start with you, Kate.
And I, I'm,
I think Dominic will correct me.
I think that the equity fund is strictly
for the patient side of it.
But I wanted to clarify what you were
meaning about the models in the community,
just the last part of it that you were
talking about,
because I am interested in what you what
you meant by that.
Yeah.
I mean, these are interlocking pieces.
And you're right,
the the fund doesn't tell us what models
like is this for group work or is this
for one-on-one or, you know, it's just OK,
here's some money.
And then that's what we're talking about
now is how can this be used, you know,
to help the most people?
But but that all, you know,
what makes it affordable?
Is it, you know,
like there's some models of psychedelic
therapy and even places like Oregon where
it's just priced out of individuals
ability to pay.
And it's great if we can get systems like
Medicaid to cover,
but also looking at how can we do the
most good with all the resources we have?
And that includes, you know,
I think in a lot of times peer support
and ongoing,
ongoing support systems can be more
effective than having like in Australia,
they were just like they have a doctor
sitting there along with two therapists
through the session.
Like those doctors are probably pretty
bored, maybe not bored, but not needed,
right?
So as we develop the systems where people,
you know, and this comes around again to,
well, when the tribes get involved,
you know, ask people, what do you want,
what do you see where this money could do
some good.
So right now,
I'm glad we're just looking at all of
this.
And there's a lot of things that we'll
find out more as it, as it all develops.
Yeah.
So I think I'm going to try to tackle
what I hear you saying,
and then I can go back to Denali's point
and Hannah's point.
I can't remember, but I, I,
Dominic can definitely correct me if I'm
wrong.
I think that this,
that the equity fund is strictly for the
patient end of it.
I'm not sure that it really has much to
do with the facilitator training side of
it.
And I'm not sure where you know,
like what that looks like.
So it sounds like there are like 3
different components to what you're
saying and, and they're great,
they're great ideas.
So what we're looking at,
it sounds like that we're trying to
figure out what to do with individuals,
individuals seeking individual treatment,
one-on-one treatment.
And maybe that is a good point to put a
pin in if there is going to be a
potential model for group therapies where
you have say, let's just put it out there,
a family who wants to join in on this,
You know, a father, you know,
grandparents like grandma,
grandpa and daughter, right?
Three of them.
And it's a family dynamic.
And they're all seeing the same
facilitator and they're all interested in
going on to this treatment together.
I can see that that based in more
traditional healing might be effective.
And maybe that might be something to
consider in the future.
I'm not sure if that's where the equity
fund would go,
but I think it's a good kind of like sub
heading to what we could potentially look
for in the future or something that we
could look into now as a way to tie into
ancestral Indigenous wisdom and healing,
but also to provide support for the
community.
Because now, as they say,
you're feeding more birds with one piece
of bread and maybe this,
there might be something to that.
I think that that is very valid,
if that's what you're saying.
Yeah, I, I just,
I'm actually just now reading the agenda
and recognizing that the agenda is asking
for specific recommendations for this
fund.
And, you know,
I sort of backed up to the big picture.
So, you know, having said that,
we'll do the best we can to recreate the
recommendations because that's the job of
this committee and and it's what the
agenda says.
So sorry if I sidetracked anything.
Oh, no, no, no.
I was just,
I was going to go ahead and go an honor
that this is actually a really
interesting point.
So just kind of like putting a pin in it
that this might be something for the
future, because I think it's very valid.
It's it's you're you're right.
And especially also with the tribes where,
you know,
we're still kind of waiting on the more
formal invitation of talking to them.
So we're we're going to get to that.
But you're right, you know, it's,
it's always just been like,
how do we address this?
And so putting these things in place
first and saying that this is what we
came up with.
And then also kind of all right,
this is what we came up while we were
waiting for the more formal,
while we were waiting for the sit down,
while we were waiting for everybody to
kind of congregate essentially,
then we can kind of look at these things.
Because if I,
if we were just kind of wait for
everybody to show up to sit down to eat,
then we would never,
we'd never get around to eating.
So we are looking at,
to addressing the needs of the tribe.
But I feel like, you know, it's, it's,
it's up to New Mexico to figure out what
we have And then with input from the
tribes, what they feel like, you know,
they need support in how do they need
support?
But it also goes to the same with like
the rural communities,
what do they need for support?
To me, it's always education, providing,
you know,
as much information as we possibly can so
that people have the agency to help
themselves as necessary.
I think that agency idea kind of goes
back to a little bit of what Denali was
saying.
I don't want to just sit there and put
like, my, my,
my input and all these things,
but a part of it is the agency of.
Yeah,
I'm not familiar with all of the
bureaucracy of navigating anything even
just to kind of figure out how to create
a license or of a business or get an LLC.
That's just a headache more of the night.
And no one's,
they say they have all these videos to
help, but they're not help.
So I,
I can understand the frustration of that
someone really wants something.
And I think that kind of goes back to
Hannah's point of the reciprocity of.
What we really want to seek and how we're
going to sacrifice something of ourselves
to be able to get the thing that we know
we need.
I don't want to say that that's the
bureaucracy,
that that's the sacrifice to your sanity
to kind of go through that.
But I do believe that there's possibly a
way that we can figure out and a
recommendation to the department.
Is there a way to kind of facilitate that?
It's like a one step, I don't know, I'm,
I'm not familiar with the bureaucracy.
I,
I have a headache on my own trying to
create my own business.
But I think that's a really valid point
of, you know,
is there a way to streamline this a
little bit while also being able to help
support our community?
And as far as the psycho assessment
process,
that might also be helpful for a
different committee that I'm neglecting
to think about what the name of that is
at this point.
Yeah.
So hopefully I kind of covered a little
bit of what the things that were brought
up.
It looks like Dominic has his hand up.
Thank you, Tespa.
So a couple of things on this and I just
to to sort of explain a little bit from
the bureaucratic standpoint is of course
we are trying to streamline things as
much as we can,
but also anytime funds are expended,
we have to actually justify that
expenditure.
And so like in this case and and Denali,
your point is very clear as we don't want
to have an application that's going to be
onerous and very difficult for people to
be able to apply for.
So we have been looking for other
potential markers,
so to speak that might work.
The Medicaid,
it looks like that's not going through,
but we're still talking with HCA to sort
of see if there's any way we can connect
in with that.
And that was a great idea Denali had
brought up separately outside this
committee, oh, months and months ago.
So we're still looking at that though.
But there may be other potential markers
and we'll continue to look at that.
For example, WIC,
So if someone's enrolled in WIC,
do they automatically at that point have
it or they already have that information?
Historically,
when we've had programs where income has
been a factor as far As for funding to
help with treatments or other aspects,
it's usually been things like tax returns
from the previous year.
But there are sometimes other issues with
regard to that.
For example,
some people who haven't filed their taxes
or they're late in filing their previous
year's taxes or just things like that,
that kind of come in that create an issue.
What I would say, though,
is let's not focus on that aspect right
now because we'll work through that
portion.
What we really need to figure out right
now is what will be some of these
standards.
And just to kind of give an idea is if
you look up the statistics, for example,
of what is the current cost of living in
New Mexico?
And of course,
this varies from different communities,
whether it's in, you know,
Carlsbad or in Los Alamos,
which Los Alamos has probably the highest
cost of living in the state,
or to Las Cruces or Albuquerque, Santa Fe,
you're going to have a little bit of a
difference.
But the estimates really range about 46,
000 to about 50,
000 for a single individual for cost of
living.
And then that goes up, of course,
when you have families and things like
that.
And the range actually varies quite a bit
based upon what some of their needs are
going to be,
whether it be medical things like travel,
school costs, childcare, things like that.
But when we think about that,
one of the sort of one of the areas that
keeps kind of coming up is if we look at
that annual cost for a single individual,
it really fits in with about 300% of the
poverty level.
As Desbaugh was saying earlier, it's 15,
000 and some change is what the poverty
level is for a single individual.
And by the way,
I put a chart into the and a link in the
chat earlier.
And so if we're looking at that, you know,
one of the things that we could consider
is if an individual is at 300% of the
poverty level or less,
that means they are just barely hit that
cost of living for the state.
And so is that a good marker,
a good level for us to look at and say if
someone is at that point,
then we should figure out a way through
the equity fund to pay for their
treatment.
And so I think what we really need to
start moving forward are some a little
bit firmer sort of guidelines and and
thoughts as far as what we can do there.
And and I would say with income level
first and then we start adding some of
the ideas about geography.
So do we make adjustments on the income
level based then on geography or distance
from the potential treatment location,
those sort of things and start adding
them in.
And then I just want to hit one other
point and then of course turn it back on
over to everyone else.
And this was,
it was another point that Denali had
brought up.
And, and,
and that's by you talked a little bit
about it as well is,
and this is a process portion.
Anytime the state is actually going to be
providing funds to someone through a
state agency like Department of Health,
there's really only three ways really to
kind of do that.
One, if we pay directly to the patient,
we actually have to register that
individual in our what's called the share
system,
which is the payment system and does all
of our financials and all of that.
We have to register them in there as a
vendor.
So that adds to the paperwork and the
bureaucracy.
So that becomes probably you have to get
W9 forms from people.
It can be difficult to navigate.
So that brings us the next step would
potentially to be to pay the providers
directly.
So whenever however many patients come in
and we can set it up similar to how it
works for insurance and Medicaid.
We're basically that that particular
provider enters into our system as a
vendor and then however many patients
they see in that week or month,
whatever the frequency that they want to
invoice the department,
then the department reimburses them
through that invoicing process.
And then the third way is actually
through a third party.
The the issue with regard to a third
party that I just want to raise is that
they always take a piece of that,
of how much,
however much funding passes through them
to pay out to,
whether it be to patients or providers.
They then actually take a portion of that.
And it's been a while since I've actually
done a program like that.
But there was one I was involved with
about 10 years ago.
And at that time that percentage was
about 18%.
So that with the money we have,
that means a fair amount of money goes
towards administrative processing rather
than the patients.
So these are just considerations to think
of.
The main one we've been really looking at
is as far As for the providers and it is
actually a part of what we did when we
initially proposed the budget for the
program.
We actually included one of the positions
that we included was specifically to
process those kinds of applications,
so to assist patients with doing them as
far as the application for the equity
fund and then paying providers and so
that the money goes that direction.
That just seems to be the best use for
the funds.
But again,
I could be wrong and we definitely want
to hear about it with without having
money going out of the fund into the
processing because that money then would
come out of the operating budget for the
program and without creating additional
burden for the patients through that
first system I talked about where they'd
have to register as a vendor W9,
all of that.
And so I think instead of focusing right
now on the bureaucracy side of it,
because believe me,
we want to reduce that as much as we can
for every involved.
And then what we would like to do is if
we could start with some of the
guidelines would be, and you know,
and I would say if we want to start,
we started talking about that 300% of
poverty level.
And then as people have thoughts and
ideas adjust from there.
But just to use that as a starting point,
you know, and,
and so I kind of would like to see and
Denali just asked a question in the chat.
And so, Denali,
I can't guarantee it will be there.
But if I have any influence in doing it,
yes,
that would be a position that I would be
requesting in that FY20 8 budget.
But as you know,
I can't guarantee that because it depends.
Well,
a lot of it will depend on the election.
So we'll see what happens there.
Anyway, thank you, everybody.
I think we had Hannah wanted to say, yeah,
you can go ahead, your mic is enabled.
Thank you.
Dominic,
I agree with you about leaning towards
that provider reimbursement.
Yeah,
that just intuitively felt easeful when
you said that.
And then also,
I wanted to expand upon Dez Buzz,
what she spoke to.
Yeah,
around that reciprocity and education.
So again,
this does not directly apply to these
ideas of, you know,
money funds at the moment.
I just want to invite in this deeper
level level of cultural consideration and
expand upon that very real topic of
education.
So as particular, particularly on,
you know, tribal lands,
the populations there have what we call
historical trauma recognition like or
historical trauma like from a social work
perspective,
where the historical trauma that's rooted
within their belief systems has created a
deep seated trust,
distrust of the medical systems in
addition to historically suppress
suppressing their traditional healing,
which creates a distortion of needs
through systemic oppression.
And so I'm almost wondering if there's a
need within the medical psilocybin
program for building relationship,
because what happens in social work is
with those deep seated traumas that are
systemic,
then the approach for the social worker
becomes building relationship instead of
having like a,
an assessment piece of paper,
because we're on,
we're addressing this kind of trauma
informed approach.
And and again,
for for oppressed cultures to step up and
be like,
I want to participate in this program.
There's going to be education and like a
slow unwinding and re bridging of of us
to to these to these systems of us in the
medical psilocybin program.
Yeah, I feel complete in that.
Thank you.
Thank you to kind of go back to a little
bit what Dominic was addressing as far as
like how we're going to be able to
utilize the funds.
And this is of course just my own opinion
on things, so,
but this is just an example.
So the average,
the national average cost of living
according to the wonderful Internet is
$78,535.
I don't know anybody who makes that much
money.
I mean, I do,
but I also don't that's the cost of
living nationally.
Here in Santa Fe, it is $87,959.
Again,
I don't know anyone making that amount of
money.
According to again wonderful Internet,
Albuquerque is 75,393.6 Espanola.
Somehow I have no idea how this is even
possible.
71,466 and 8585 cents.
That's outrageous.
My ex-husband was trying to get a job in
Ruedo so for $40,000 with a $202,
000 bonus sign on.
So these numbers are just insane.
And the national poverty average is $15,
000.
I can't remember the name of the person.
I know this is a little bit off track,
but it's just like how we're supposed to
be able to help fund these things is that
the actual cost of, of,
of living isn't the, the, the,
the average poverty line actual around is
like closer to like $100,000.
Maybe, maybe it's,
maybe that's an exaggeration, but it's,
it's way above $15,000.
I don't know who came up with these
numbers or what kind of magic math
they're using that $15,
000 is the poverty line,
but these are the numbers that we have to
work with.
And that's just as an as an example for
why being able to help provide this
medicine in the way that we're doing it
and for the people who are seeking this
particular route,
just to kind of emphasize that because
there is the underground,
but this is also for the people who are
seeking it in this particular way.
And this is how New Mexico State is
providing its way to help its citizens
who want to go this route,
who want to and to be able to provide it
for as many people as possible.
And that does that does definitely
include our native populations.
And to that point,
what Hannah was bringing up, yes,
as a Denev person,
one of the things that we do understand
is this idea of essentially making us
wrong for the medicine that we've already
been using for hundreds of years.
And so in this particular way,
the state of New Mexico,
we're trying to move forward as best we
can for say, the rest of U.S.
law abiding citizens who have for such a
long period of time been told that this
is wrong.
And so we are having to battle the stigma
not only from decades of the government
telling us that it's wrong,
but this is the time and the opportunity
that is happening within the state,
one of the first three states, to do so,
to bridge that gap and to unwind the
effects of what was imposed on its people
prior to 1912.
So a lot of this is very historical.
And even what we're doing right now as a
government and within the state of New
Mexico and the DoH is very historical in
a lot of ways.
It does have a financial responsibility.
And that's where what we're trying to do
right now.
What is the responsible financial way
that we are taking care of the citizens
who choose this route,
who choose to to utilize this opportunity
that New Mexico is providing in its own
framework to unwind that and to move
closer to what I would consider more
equal footing across the board.
It's gonna take a lot of us to move past
the fear from every side,
both native non-native people moving in
everywhere to really fight to figure out
what we need to do.
But we have to do it in the specific way.
And right now the job is,
what are we gonna do with the money that
we have?
How is it going to be taken care of?
How do we provide the support,
support systems and what does that look
like?
So, and it has to be very, very specific.
That's, that's, that's the call.
That is the issue at hand.
That is the right thing to do.
I think Denali had her hand up.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you, Desba,
for that and for sharing so much of your
own experience as well.
I'm wondering as you were going through,
like the cost of living.
I just wonder if it might be a helpful
tool for the committee to make this
decision to have kind of aggregated how
like what different programs in New
Mexico use as metrics of eligibility.
And I'm wondering too,
I think this is a question for the
department, whether that,
whether there's resources within the
state,
whether that's like the DFA or
Legislative Council service
representative for the department,
if there's an opportunity to ask for
collaboration to create some kind of
aggregated tool for the subcommittee to
like have a more global understanding.
And by global,
I mean within our own state,
but like how in,
across programs in the state are we
creating eligibility based on need?
And I,
I just feel like there's some learning I
could do about how how other programs
operate and it would be helpful for to
inform the decisions that we have to make.
Yeah, I think that that's a good idea.
As far as I mean, and I'm some,
I hope someone can verify this
differently because there's the
eligibility for the be well,
which is like a completely different
thing.
But it also triggers the thing for the
Medicaid and then it decides whether or
not you want to and then you have to deal
with Medicaid and you also have to deal
with deal with be well.
And that is so much brain power.
It's.
Yeah.
And I feel like trying to just find
something that has worked well enough to
figure that out would be helpful in terms
of this.
All right.
So I think it was Dominic who his hand
shot up first.
Yeah, thank you.
And Denali,
that's exactly what I was talking about
when I was saying that we're looking for
those other markers so we're don't have
to necessarily duplicate what's happening.
What I hear you saying that was if we
could sort of create some sort of a chart
or table or even summary of some of those
points really for this committee.
And we can definitely do that as we move
forward.
But part of it is we have to figure out
what some of those potential markers
might be.
And and that'll help from a bureaucratic
sort of standpoint for being able to
ensure we're processing things forward.
But I don't think that's going to
necessarily fit in all cases because we
are going to have other situations where,
as like Hanna was saying,
is we need to be looking at some areas
with regard to, you know, the,
the different regional differences.
So, but in any case, what, what I really,
because we just have about 15 minutes
left.
I, I would really ask if there's,
if we can sort of get a starting point,
you know,
and kind of start moving from there,
talking as far as,
whether it be income level or otherwise.
And then as we get that other information,
we of course can move that.
So not adopting here's what it will be,
but start talking about the specifics
because we can continue to talk about the
the other aspects of it for months,
quite honestly.
But if we don't start laying down some,
at least some marker points,
we're not ever going to get,
we're not ever going to move forward
because we can talk about the equity
issues and the lack of equity that we
have in the state for years and never
stop.
And to that point, Dominic,
it sounds like what we're needing to do
is just decide to establish like what is
just putting something baseline down that
it's, it's based on the poverty levels,
which, you know,
I have no problem with saying that that's
like the starting point.
You know, it's like, yes,
we're gonna base it on that.
I think the only thing I would have is,
is that just the standard for for all the
low income programs in New Mexico?
I mean,
is that across the board for WIC and SNAP
and you know,
what are the criteria for VWL and
Medicaid?
Are they all utilizing the same one and
whether or not their percentage is above
or below?
Because like I said, you know,
the cost of living here,
even if you say the $15,
000 that cuts off to me.
That's what I'm trying to say is like
that cuts off people like me.
Let's just say it for me, for example,
that cuts off me.
I'm not at the poverty level,
but I'm also not making a lot of money.
So where does that put me?
A mother of two?
I mean,
a mother of one who's who definitely is
still struggling to pay rent, right?
Who could definitely not afford to have a
treatment of $100 or copay,
no matter if that's what the the
guidelines say that I'm supposed to
somehow pay $100.
I can tell you right now I can't.
So I think that that's maybe what we're
trying to look at, if I'm not mistaken.
Yeah.
And and what I was saying on that despot
is if somebody is at for example,
300% of the poverty level or less than
the fund would cover their treatment
costs.
Now if it covers the travel and all of
that, that may be different.
So for example in your situation with a
household of two that would put it at
about 64000 a year.
So if you were making less than 64000,
then that would be the treatment would be
covered.
But that's just a starting point.
We can also look at,
and I had mentioned this,
I think in a few meetings back is say
then for example,
someone's at 350% poverty level,
maybe then the guidance is that we pay
for up to, you know,
say 75% of the treatment cost and then at
400%, you know,
and I think those are the things that we
need to start thinking about.
It is how much will that do always
keeping in mind it depends on how many
people end up applying for this out of
that total pocket of fund.
And and that's why I've been saying we
should look at it regarding the poverty
levels in the state, not in the nation,
because the nation also would be much
bigger.
Oh, and Hannah just put something up.
I missed that, Hannah.
So yes,
looking at the poverty levels between
that and we could say it's going to be
based even on the more local on the
county level and that we could see about
trying to come up with what that chart is.
I'm not sure who might have it.
I do know I've seen it before.
And so looking at that aspect where we
say within the county level,
here's what the poverty levels are for
say, you know,
and I'll just say it because I was just
talking about Roswell the other day,
but the Chavez County.
And so we say,
what is the poverty level in Chavez
County and then base it upon that.
So varying it with regard to those local
areas.
No,
I think that's a really smart idea
because that was a reason why I didn't
realize why,
but that was the reason why I was
bringing up Espanola.
You know, that's where my hometown is.
You know, I'm living in Santa Fe.
The reason why my parents couldn't live
in Los Alamos is because it's too
expensive and that's why everyone ends up
in Espanola.
But you know, you,
if you're going by county,
then that definitely makes a lot more
sense because if you average everything
out in New Mexico, I mean,
Santa Fe and Los Alamos,
shoot everything up and it's it's
impossible.
I think that would be a good place to
start.
Is anybody else, Greg?
All right, whoops.
OK, let me get your mic here, Greg.
All right.
You should be able to unmute.
Hey, I've been kind of in and out today.
And is my mic working?
Yes.
Yep.
OK.
I've been trying to find a way.
So I don't think I've heard this
specifically said.
So I think it might be interesting and
bold and complicated to earmark a chunk
of that money,
say like half and make it reparation
style spending.
So develop education and outreach to to
specific ethnic or other group
communities and say, look,
we are giving you this money.
This is how you can use it.
And like spend that money in a very
specific distributive manner.
People would have to apply and fit into
the category of acceptance to to receive
the therapy or whatever.
But it's like take that first chunk of it
and be like,
here is money that we were just putting
back into this community.
It's like it our our native populations,
our first peoples in this state are not
traditionally using psilocybin.
This would be a new modality.
But like,
let's take this modality that that we are
creating and say, hey,
if this is useful to you,
we want you to receive this.
Just brainstorming,
but I would love to see the word
reparations be used.
And then I see.
Hannah,
it looks like you're in agreement with
what Greg was saying.
Denali, did you want to say something?
Oh,
we're just wrapping up here really
quickly.
So kinda Denali.
Yeah, grateful for that contribution.
And circling back to the comment that I
made earlier about the statute and the
limits of the statute, I think,
I think that's where the rub would be
right.
Is, is not that income is the only factor,
but it has to be an eligibility criteria.
And maybe there's a way within what
you're imagining, Greg, that that works.
But like at the the starting point of the
inquiry,
the way that I read what the department
is required to do in terms of creating
eligibility, yes,
we can consider other factors.
But like the the principal eligibility
factor is tied to income and not some
other right,
like historical oppression or other
things that are really relevant the way
that we decide to share resources in the
state.
But that's my only contribution.
OK, thank you.
We just have a couple minutes.
I wanted to say thank you all for
everyone and your contributions.
Just to kind of put a little pin on that.
Yeah, I think that's a great idea, Greg,
just to kind of put it out there into the
future because these things,
this what we say,
can possibly cast spell into the future.
I definitely believe that.
You know,
I think for the future it might be a good,
a good strategy for people to kind of
understand that that might be what it's
worth.
Reparations are definitely important.
And I think that that's a good place.
And then also to Denali's point,
we do have to base what we what we do
with the money on the limitations and the
criteria for which it was provided.
But I think it it definitely is a great
idea.
I know other places have done the same
thing.
And I can't remember if it was Oregon or
maybe it was Colorado.
That or, you know,
allow the tribes to be able to fund what
they felt was necessary.
But again, you know,
we're going to wait to see what have
those conversations with the governors
when we can make those appointments and
those invitations happen.
That would be great.
Thank you for your time.
I think we're probably going to try to
come up with meeting.
Is it OK if we don't come up with one for
right now?
Because I know we are meeting.
I don't even know when we're meeting next.
I think it's in May for the board meeting.
But we're what we're gonna do is we're
gonna try to get an in person meeting set
up.
I think that's gonna be my next,
but I have to I have to coordinate with
the coordinator for that.
And in the meantime,
definitely take the the e-mail medical
psilocybin at doh.nm.
gov to talk a little bit about what you
had a comment on.
Use the subject line as a way to kind of
inform the committee what it's about or
the date of the committee meeting and the
name of the committee meeting.
Again, thank you for your time.
I hope you have a great rest of your day.
And if there's any closing remarks from
Dominic and the admins, go for it.
Yeah, thank you.
Just I think it's fine to hold off a
little bit on a meeting until we get that
other one set up with that.
And and just as a note,
I had put it in the chat in the very
beginning,
but I know some people joined a little
later.
So just in case they haven't seen it is
we did have the rules on the propagation
and laboratories did publish today.
So if you've been involved in some of
those committees and I and I did put that
in earlier,
but the other thing that I just wanted to
put in,
and we'll put these into the chat so that
people will have them is don't forget to
go to the website to see as far as
upcoming meetings.
And so we've got that in the chat right
now.
And like I said, in just a moment,
I'll get the link about it's to a website
for where you can see the public notice
and where you can see the proposed rules.
And so I've just got that in the chat now
as well.
So look forward to everything else
happening.
We've got a lot still happening in the
next few months.
And this is great conversation and some
great ideas.
And now we just need to start moving
things forward.
So thank you everyone.
Hope you all have a great day.